Let's continue now. So, דף כ"ו עמוד ב'. Daf Chaf Vav Amud
Bet. Okay, אמר
רב הונא אמר רב. Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav.
We're still don't we don't worry we only have hopefully if we
get fast enough further far enough today we will finish this topic
today. But the rest of this until the next משנה Mishnah is
this issue about this unspecified pile of money. אמר רב הונא אמר
רב Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav לא שנו אלא מעות. Lo Shanu
Ela Maot. This idea that if you have unspecified pile of money
that was going to be used for חטאת Chatat and שלמים Shelamim
of a נזיר Nazir and the guy dies or the נזירות Nezirut
was annulled by the husband, that then it goes towards an עולה.
Olah. That's only if it was a pile of money. Okay, אבל
בבהמה Aval Bebehemah if it was animals הרי היא כמפורשת. Harei Hi
Kimforeshit. It's like it's explicit. Now, what's the case of animals? Let
me explain. What's the case of animals? So, a lot of these
long תוספותים Tosafotim here are just to get basic פשט Pshat in
the גמרא Gemara because it's a very terse גמרא. Gemara. So תוספות
Tosafot goes through all the possibilities. Maybe the animals were the animals
that a נזיר Nazir is supposed to bring? A lamb, a male
lamb, a female lamb, a ram and so on. But if that
were true then it would be so obvious. Then you'd sanctify all
the animals and each animal,
the עולה, Olah, חטאת Chatat and שלמים Shelamim are all different animals.
So it would be self-obvious of course it's מפורש Mefurash this is
for that sacrifice this is for that each one is a different
animal. Okay, so what תוספות Tosafot says is it sounds like what
the גמרא Gemara is talking about is that actually no what you
have is you have three cows here. Okay? You have animals that
maybe are in the world of
sacrifices—wouldn't work if they were let's say three pigs—you got three cows,
okay, but none of them are relevant for this sacrifice. And somehow
you say I am sanctifying all of these animals for the purpose
of bringing my sacrifices. And what basically that's going to mean is
you're going to have to redeem the value, transfer the value or
sell it, get the proceeds and use the money to buy your
sacrifices. Now the other interesting הלכה Halachah that תוספות Tosafot works out
which I'll just tell you because the גמרא's Gemara's going to distinguish
between whether the animals have a blemish or don't have a blemish
is the following interesting question. If I go ahead and I say
I am sanctifying this lovely here digital recorder to use to bring
my עולה. Olah.
I'm going to bring an עולה Olah from the funds of this.
So fine so what I do is I go ahead I sell
it or the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash sells it or whatever I
redeem the money I get the proceeds the value transfers to the
proceeds I get from the sale and then I use that money
to go ahead and buy the animal that I need to buy.
That would be normally okay. It doesn't—it's not קדושת בדק הבית. Kedushat
Bedek Habayit. It's not like I donated this to the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash and it can sell it and use it for its
upkeep or for its operating funds. This I could but that's not
what I did. I actually gave this recorder the קדושה Kedushah of
an עולה. Olah. Okay great but you don't bring recorders as עולות.
Olot. So that קדושה Kedushah transfers to the money like when I
set aside the money for my קרבנות. Korbanot. It has the קדושה
Kedushah of the קרבן, Korban, okay, but it's not going to be
used itself. You're going to then transfer it eventually to the animal.
That's what would normally happen. Let's say I go ahead and I
sanctify my goat my cow, okay,
for for my קרבן נזיר Korban Nazir which has to be a
sheep. Okay so can I just go ahead and sell the cow
and use the proceeds?
Why not? Because if let's say I had actually here's three scenarios.
One is I sanctify the cow for the בדק הבית Bedek Habayit
for for the operating funds upkeep of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
They just sell it, right? It's just a cow. Fine. It's just
like I sanctified my car. Here's scenario number two. I sanctify the
cow to bring the cow itself as an עולה. Olah. Okay? In
that case if I would want to not bring that cow I
couldn't just transfer the money I'd have to wait for the cow
to get a מום. Mum. Here is an interesting middle so if
it's just being used as a as something as an object of
like not in its identity as a cow basically just as an
object of value like a car you sell it right away. If
it's being used because the animal itself was going to be brought
as a
קרבן Korban the קדושה Kedushah can only be transferred if it has
a מום. Mum. Let's say I gave it the קדושה Kedushah of
a קרבן Korban but not for it itself to be brought as
a קרבן. Korban. Right? I gave it the קדושה Kedushah of an
עולה Olah but the עולה Olah of a נזיר Nazir that can
only be brought from a sheep. So because it has the קדושה
Kedushah that's relevant to the world of קרבנות Korbanot and if it
itself was a קרבן Korban that קדושה Kedushah could not be removed
without a מום. Mum. Now that I gave it this קדושה Kedushah
for—does that mean that the קדושה Kedushah can't be removed without a
מום Mum or do we say look, since you're not going to
bring this cow itself you can just automatically sell it and transfer
the קדושה Kedushah you don't need a מום? Mum? So that's what
תוספות Tosafot tries to sort of figure out and work out and
based on this סוגיא Sugya that's what we're going to see in
a minute—you haven't even seen the גמרא Gemara yet—תוספות Tosafot concludes that
yes because it's relevant to the world of קרבנות Korbanot because in
theory it could be brought itself even though that's not the קדושה
Kedushah you gave it right now you cannot get the קדושה Kedushah
off of that cow even though it's coming for a sheep עולה
Olah until the cow has a מום. Mum. So if you had
sanctified I don't know a chicken, okay, with the קדושה Kedushah of
an עולה Olah you could sell it without—you just sell it to
the farmer you get the money—but because it's a cow and the
cow is relevant to the world of קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay, even though
you did not give it the קדושה kedushah for it itself to
be brought, the קדושה kedushah cannot be removed without it somehow being
out, removed from the world of קרבנות. korbanot. That's the only way
it can sort of free itself from that קדושה. kedushah. Otherwise, it's
just too relevant to that קדושה kedushah that it cannot be transferred
just through an act of sale. Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosafot
says. The reason that's going to be relevant before I take the
questions, let's just read the line in the גמרא Gemara which makes
this all very relevant. So the next line of the גמרא Gemara
says the following and then I'll explain anyway what this has to
do with whether how the funds are used or not. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב נחמן הא דאמרינן בבהמה הרי
היא כמפורשת. Amar Rav Nachman: Ha de-amrinan be-behemah harei hi ke-mefureshet. That
statement of Rav, that a בהמה behemah is like it's already been
designated, לא שנו אלא בתמימה, lo shanu ela bitmimah, that's only if
it's an unblemished בהמה. behemah. And that type of a case, again,
even if we're dealing with cows here, but the money cannot be
the, they cannot just be simply sold. You have to wait for
them to get a blemish and that's what gives them a different
status. אבל בעלת מום, Aval ba'alat mum, if these cows had a
blemish, okay, הרי היא כסתומה, harei hi kistumah, then it's like unspecified
funds. Now, okay, so now I've laid the groundwork for us to
understand the difference, that even if we're dealing with cows and animals
that cannot themselves be brought for this sacrifice, why it matters if
there's a blemish or not a blemish or why there's a difference
between blemish and not a blemish, whether they can be sold immediately
or not or whether you have to wait for them to get
a blemish. But what still doesn't explain is why does that make
a difference for our הלכה halachah here about whether it's considered like
סתומה stumah or not סתומה, stumah, whether it's considered like unspecified moneys.
If I sanctified three cows and eventually, whether they do or don't
have a blemish, eventually I'm going to sell them and use the
proceeds and divide that proceeds between the קרבנות korbanot that I have
to bring, why should it be considered like it's סתומה, stumah, like
it's מפורשת? mefureshet? Like it's already like it's been designated. What do
you mean it's been designated? I mean, it's not like this cow
is going to ultimately, money's going to go to that one and
this cow money's going to go to that one. I'm going to
sell all three cows and I'm going to divide up the money,
right? And even if I was going to do one cow per
sacrifice, which cow is for which? Why is it like it's מפורשת?
mefureshet? It's all unspecified. Why can't, why wouldn't it have the same
הלכה? halachah? Okay, so that's the question and that's what we're going
to be dealing with now is things that somehow don't have the
status of unspecified and it's not clear why not. So there basically
are two answers why not. One is the simple הלכה למשה מסיני
halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai answer. You know, according to the idea that all
of this is a הלכה למשה מסיני, halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai, the הלכה
halachah was said by money. It wasn't said by things that weren't
money. So if I'm sanctifying something that's not money, even though it
really is סתומה, stumah, it's unspecified, but this הלכה halachah that you
get to reuse that money for an עולה olah if it has
the חטאת chatat money mixed up in it or whatever, that was
a special הלכה halachah only said by cash. It wasn't said by
things that aren't cash. Not cash, okay, it's not מפורשת. mefureshet. That's
a funny way of saying it. It is סתומה, stumah, but it
doesn't matter. The הלכה halachah wasn't said by this and what you'll
have to do is throw it all out into the ים המלח
Yam HaMelach because it has חטאת chatat money mixed up with הלכה
halachah only said by cash. Fine, but if it's הלכה halachah only
said by cash, who cares if it's animals that have a blemish?
Animals that have a blemish last I checked also weren't cash. So
the question is, what is the line between cash and not cash?
And basically, it's actually, there's an interesting word. It took me a
while to realize this in when I was in Israel, right? What's
the word for cash in Israel? מזומן. mezuman. I like before I
knew that, I said what the heck is מזומן? mezuman? Ready? What
do you mean מזומן? mezuman? I didn't understand why that means cash.
Okay, but what it basically means is something that is very easily
immediately transferable like for the goods that you want, right? So the
basic thinking is like this: something that is like readily sellable is
in the same category and can easily be liquidated and turned into
cash is basically in the same category as cash. So if you've
got animals that have a blemish and all you've got to do
is turn around and sell it to someone, right? Again, assuming there's
a reasonable market for them or whatever, that has a status of
cash. So the הלכה halachah was said by something like animals with
a blemish. It wasn't, maybe it wouldn't have been said by I
don't know, something like my house that put up for sale, you've
got to wait for the best bid. That's something, yeah, I mean
I could sell for cash if I really took a serious loss,
but it's not easily liquid, you know, liquidated and easily turned into,
turned into cash. That's not cash. An animal without a blemish that
has to wait for the blemish before it could be sold because
of the laws of קדושה, kedushah, that is not in the cash
category. That does not, is not easily transferable into cash. So that
is two ways of understanding what we're about to look at. We're
going to say certain things don't have this הלכה halachah
that you can go ahead and what do you call it? That
you can use the money towards an עולה, olah, this unspecified pile.
It was only a הלכה halachah said by cash, not things that
aren't cash. And anything that can easily be liquidated and turned into
cash is considered cash. But animals that need a blemish before they're
sold, they're not in that category. Now that doesn't give the logic
for it. It just says in a formal way, it's limited to
cash. Okay, the other thing to say and then I know there
are a few questions, but the other thing to say is if
you want a type of a logic for it, and this is
what... He says here's the logic. The logic is, if it's going
to take me a long time before I can offload this stuff,
so the stuff is going to be around my house a long
time. At a certain stage when I have these three cows grazing
and I'm waiting, waiting, waiting for them to get a blemish מום,
mum, maybe I'm thinking in my mind, oh, I'm going to sell
Bessie over there, she's going to be for the עולה, ola, and
I'm going to sell this other one and that one's going to
be for the חטאת, chatat, and in my mind I've somehow already
like pre-designated, you know, how I'm going to use that money. And
if that comes about, then it stops having this status of סתומה,
stuma, then it becomes מפורשת, mefureshet, because I've already decided the funds
from that animal is going to this one and the funds from
that animal is going to that. Now that sounds funny, that sounds
like a very like a rabbinic type of a concern, and what
תוספות Tosafot deals with is, and even if I thought that, if
I didn't say that, does it really change the status? I mean,
you know, I haven't said it yet, who cares if I'm thinking
that in my mind? So that's the way he tries to give
some logic to this, but the easier thing is just to make
this a formal rule that what the גמרא Gemara is saying is,
this says only by cash, something that's going to take time to
liquidate and to you know get the cash the money for and
to ultimately buy the other thing, that this הלכה halacha was not
said for, and that's not considered the idea that you use the
money for an עולה. ola. In that case, you would throw it
all out, you'd have to treat it because there's חטאת chatat money
in here, you'd have to throw it all out. Okay, so now
I'm done with my introduction. Was there a question?
And the question is this. You're saying the case was that I
can buy five cows or whatever it is. Right, exactly. So
this, I guess in my mind, my question is, doesn't that hearken
back, I think it was מחלוקת בית שמאי ובית הלל הקדש בטעות?
machloket Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel hekdesh b'taut? Or isn't that הקדש בטעות?
hekdesh b'taut?
It's not תוספות, Tosafot, I knew that I wasn't going to bring
the things
themselves. But as
same as setting aside a pile of money, I set aside three
cows. Okay, so that's his point, okay. אבל נסכא לא. aval naska
lo. But if it was נסכא, naska,
which was basically like a bar of a bar of precious metal,
a bar of silver, a bar of gold or something like that,
that would not meaning would not be a would not be a
problem that basically something like that, hold on I keep on getting
confused which way this one goes. No, that would that also would
not be considered like cash. That would be something that you would
actually you'd have to wait until you got the right price for
it and so on. So that's sort of like the animals without
the blemish. That's also not cash.
Why is that not like a recorder?
Well, again, there's a difference between a recorder, you know, now we
put these things on eBay or Craigslist, we can probably sell them
pretty quickly, but there's not like as much of a ready market
for recorders as there are for cows. You live in an agricultural
society, you just go to the market next week and somebody's going
to you know sell your cows, right?
So cows are more readily available than a bar of gold.
That seems to be the assumption. And or right, or maybe it's
harder to ensure you're getting your right price, although you would think
precious metals, it goes by weight, maybe it's easier, I don't know.
But that's the assumption here, that these types of things are things
you have to wait more to get the right price for that
don't sell as easily. Okay.
So that's why they were so favorable for coins, because coins had
a certification.
Ah, so you knew the exact weight and you knew the purity
of it and so on. Right, okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר
אפילו נסכא. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar afilu naska. No, no, no,
even bar of metal is considered something that is cash for this
purpose, and therefore it has this הלכה halacha that the money goes
towards an עולה. ola. אבל שורא דקורי, aval shura d'korei, but if
you've got a pile of like beams of you know of lumber,
in that case, beams of wood, לא, lo, not, because again, I
don't know, like you know, that's something that you have to find
the person that's looking to construct a house and he's got to
inspect it, whatever it is, that's not as liquid as these other
things. So it's an interesting question of how liquid something has to
be in order to be considered cash, in order to have this
special הלכה. halacha. Fine. אמר ליה רב שימי בר אשי לרב פפא,
amar lei Rav Shimi bar Ashi l'Rav Papa, Rav Shimi bar Ashi
says to Rav Papa, מאי טעמא דרבנן דאמרי, mai tama d'Rabbanan d'amri,
what's the reason of the Rabbis that say, you know, that it
only applies to money? דמעות ולא בהמה ולא נסכא, d'maot v'lo behema
v'lo naska, because they say this הלכה halacha was said by money,
money means not animals, again with that you have to wait for
a blemish at least, okay, and not bars
of of precious metal, מעות maot and money ולא שורא, v'lo shura,
not like a or שורא, shura, not a you know a pile
of lumber, not lumber, a pile of like beams, as so that's
what they say. It has to be only money, and these things
aren't considered cash. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's true, מעות ולא
עופות. maot v'lo ofot.
Let's say money and not birds. Now, what does he mean by
birds? You think okay, I'm sanctifying these birds to be used for
my קרבן נזיר. korban nazir. All right, well, you know, maybe we
would say that again would depend on how readily transferable birds would
be, you know, to cash and so on. But what's going to
clear from the גמרא Gemara and that's what takes up this huge
תוספות Tosafot which means that our דף daf is going to go
quickly. is that it doesn't read in the ongoing discussion. We're not
just talking like you sanctified some chickens or something like that, okay?
But what we're talking about is that this other הלכה halacha which
I think actually
was mentioned the other day, which was if a woman, well the
classic case is a woman, but anybody who has to bring two
birds, an עולה olah and a חטאת, chatas, classic case is a
woman who's given birth, and she sanctifies the bird, she doesn't have
to specify which is the עולה, olah, which is the חטאת. chatas.
She can either do it at the time she sanctifies them or
the כהן kohein is the one that specifies when the כהן kohein
brings them. That's the הלכה. halacha. Okay, so what we're going to
say is that the question here is, now I gotta remind myself
because תוספות Tosafos has three possibilities and I'll tell you what the
third one is at the very end of this תוספות. Tosafos. Hold
on.
One minute.
It's
such a
long
תוספות, Tosafos, sorry.
Okay,
so here's the question תוספות Tosafos asks. What would be the case
in the following case? We've been focusing so far on the money
of a נזיר nazir or whatever that has to be for three
קרבנות, korbanos, the נזיר nazir dies, what do you use the money
for? Let's say we had another case. A woman went ahead, she
was obligated in a קרבן korban for יולדת, yoledes, two birds. She
brought the two birds. One was going to be a חטאת, chatas,
one was going to be an עולה. olah. She didn't specify which
was which. Okay, she would have brought it to the כהן, kohein,
the כהן kohein would have specified. Then the woman died before she
was able to bring it. What do you do with those two
birds? So what would you think you do with those two birds?
Since it's
a חטאת, chatas,
the woman
died it can't be
brought.
Right, one is a חטאת, chatas, one is an עולה, olah, so
maybe you bring it to the כהן kohein and let the כהן
kohein decide which one is an עולה olah and bring that and
maybe the other one get rid of, right?
Because she died, right? She died. But you said the other day
if somebody dies the offering can't be brought.
Can't be brought a חטאת, chatas, you can bring the עולה. olah.
Right. So you would assume that since if she was alive she
would bring it to the כהן, kohein, the כהן kohein would pick
out, would decide which is the חטאת, chatas, which is an עולה,
olah, she died, let the כהן kohein do the same thing, right?
Okay, but how about this is a possibility. Let's consider those two
birds like the pile of unspecified money that had in it a
חטאת chatas and an עולה, olah, and let's say that both birds
now become an עולה. olah. Okay, like the pile of money that
has a חטאת chatas and an עולה olah mixed up in it
and you bring from that pile you bring an עולה, olah, so
let's now make both birds into an עולה, olah, okay? That's the,
that would be the alternative. Okay, so the question is, if you
were to consider this pile to be like סתומים, stumim, okay, like
unspecified, like a normal case of סתומים, stumim, maybe we should say
that that should be the הלכה. halacha. So that's the question that
the גמרא Gemara is actually going to explore, okay? And so now
what, so let's take a look, let's read the next line.
But what's the difference between that and the funds being unspecified?
Well,
that's the question. Since we're already saying that the idea of unspecified
funds has some of these arbitrary limits, like it's only money and
it's not cows and it's not this and it's not that. What
if it was birds? Okay, if you had these birds which basically
had קדושת חטאת kedushas chatas and an עולה olah mixed in here,
now the difference is obvious because in the case of birds the
beings themselves are going to be brought as opposed to using the
proceeds to buy something, okay? So you could say if the thing
itself has that potential קדושה, kedusha, you know, you can't transfer, you
know, the קדושה kedusha doesn't transform in the thing itself that was
going to be brought. But anyway, but we're going to step back
and we're going to say, look, exactly that, you know, maybe we
should say there isn't a difference and maybe we should say bring
them both as an עולה. olah. But maybe, since you've just demonstrated
that you have all these arbitrary rules here, it only is money
and not things like this and not things like that and not
things like that, so maybe also in the bird case, that's also
something that you would be, would not fit into this category and
And because maybe it's a very limited category and maybe you would
not be able to bring both of the birds as an עולה.
olah. So that's the question. Our initial assumption would have been that
these two birds are like מעות סתומים. maot stumim. You have the
potential, you have a חטאת chatas and an עולה olah mixed up
in these two birds, the person died, we should treat it like
מעות סתומים maot stumim and we should get to bring both of
them as an עולה. olah. But given that you've just told me
how narrow your category is and you're excluding all these other things,
maybe we should exclude a case of birds as well and not
allow them to be brought both as an עולה. olah. That's the
question. Okay? So let's see. Now they haven't even been designated yet,
that's why they're like סתומים. stumim. Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay, אלא מעתה, ela meata, that's true, מעות ולא עופות, maot velo
ofot, let's say that it won't apply to a case of non-specified
birds, that you won't be able to bring both of those as
an עולה. olah. וכי תימא הכי נמי, v'chi teima hachi nami, maybe
that's true, maybe it's true, if the woman dies or whatever, you
don't get to bring them both as an עולה. olah. אלא הא
דאמר רב חסדא, ela hadamar Rav Chisda, but רב חסדא Rav Chisda
taught: אין
הקינין מתפרשות אלא או בלקיחת בעלים או בעשיית הכהן. ein hakinim mitparshot
ela o belakichat bealim o baasiyat hakohen. The birds do not get
their identity, do not get explicated, right? מתפרשות mitparshot is the opposite
of סתום. satum. סתום satum is מפורשת. meforeshet. They don't get explicated
and they don't get identified either only at the time that they're
purchased by the owner or when the כהן kohen actually brings it.
Okay, now הא אמאי, ha amai, but why is that true? המעות
קאמינא לך. hamaot kamilan lach. It should have been only money and
not birds. Now what does רב חסדא Rav Chisda say that tells
us that this idea that if the woman dies, you know, he's
talking about the woman's alive and they get either explained either at
the time of purchase or the time of the כהן kohen brought,
how is that relevant for our discussion? Since it's not so clear
at all how it's relevant for our discussion, but תוספות Tosfos says
it's because he chose to use the word מתפרשות. mitparshot. And מתפרשות
mitparshot is the opposite of סתום, satum, right? He could have said
another word. He said אין הקינין נקבעים, ein hakinim nikba'im, their identity
isn't established except when they're purchased by the person or brought by
the כהן. kohen. But he says they're not explicated, מתפרשות. mitparshot. It
means that without that stage of being identified at the time of
purchase or by the כהן, kohen, if they're not מתפרשות, mitparshot, what
is their הלכה halacha status? So it's the opposite of מפורשת, meforeshet,
סתום. satum. So he's basically implicitly what he is saying is unless
the woman hasn't said it at the time she purchased it and
the כהן kohen has yet to bring it, their status is סתום.
satum. And if that's their הלכה halacha status as סתומים, stumim, and
we have a הלכה halacha for סתומים, stumim, you've got this stuff
that's סתומים, stumim, the owner dies, what do we do with it?
You bring it as a נדבה. nedava. So the גמרא Gemara wants
to infer from the fact that he used the word מתפרשות, mitparshot,
this is the way תוספות Tosfos reads, again there's a lot of
other reads that are even worse than this, so if you're not
so satisfied with this read, it's the best of the three of
this huge תוספות. Tosfos. So the birds remain סתום satum if the
woman dies, that's what we're getting out of him, which means it
follows the normal הלכה halacha of סתומים, stumim, which means they both
go towards an עולה. olah. But he's saying but now the גמרא's
Gemara question is: why do they both go towards an עולה? olah?
You've been
so narrow in your definition: only money, not metal, not wood, not
this, not that. So let's also say not birds. Why is the
הלכה halacha that in this case both of those birds go towards
an עולה? olah? Okay, that's the question. Let's read the answer. אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to
him: ולטעמיך, uletameich, one minute, according to your reasoning, you want to
say that you want to reject my whole idea and you want
to say that it doesn't matter: money, birds, animals, bars of metal,
all of that the same הלכה halacha applies and that if it's
סתום, satum, it goes towards an עולה. olah. That's the opposite opinion,
don't have any of these limitations. If that's true, הא דתנן, ha
ditnan, that which we taught in the משנה: Mishna: רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, הביא שלש בהמות ולא פירש,
heivi shalosh behemot velo peireish, you brought three
animals and you didn't say. You brought three animals in front of
you: one male sheep, one female sheep and one ram, and you
basically said I'm sanctifying these two animals for my sacrifices as a
נזיר, nazir, as a נזיר. nazir. Now just, it just so happens
that those are the exact three animals you need. Okay, so but
you didn't explain which is which, so guess what? It all works
out, you know, if you're generic and they're the right animals, the
קדושה kedusha gets assigned appropriately. הראויה לחטאת תקרב חטאת לעולה תקרב עולה
ולשלמים תקרב שלמים. harauya lechatas tikarev chatas, leolah tikarev olah, ulishlamim tikarev
shelamim.
Each animal gets assigned for its right identity. Okay, fine, that's not
much of a חידוש, chiddush, I mean that would be a pretty
logical thing to say. But one minute, you want to say now
that this הלכה halacha of סתומים stumim applies regardless of the thing
that is non-specified, whether it's money, whether it's pieces of wood, whether
it's pieces of metal, whether it's animals, it all has the הלכה
halacha of סתומים, stumim, that's the counter argument, not to limit it
to the money idea. So if that's true, אמאי, amai, why should
this קדושה kedusha get divided like just so convenient? האמרת בהמה לאו
כמפורשת דמי, hamarta behema lav kimeforashet dami, an animal is still is
not like explicated, it's like in the category of סתום. satum. So
if it's like in the category of סתום, satum, even in this
case we should say they're all סתומים stumim and they don't have
any specific identity. Which shows us this is crazy! It's one thing
if I take three cows and cows aren't relevant to the sacrifice
and I say if I sank the proceeds of those three cows
for the proceeds to go, that has this הלכה halakha of non-specified
סתום, stum, it hasn't yet been identified which is which and then
if the guy dies, the money will go you know whatever, that's
fine. But if you got the right animals and you're sanctifying them,
of course that's not סתום, stum, of course it's going to be
defined in the proper way. Okay, so it's a such a difficult
גמרא, Gemara, I don't have a good answer to that question. I
mean, what type of question are you raising from this? Here it's
the right animals, of course they're going to be have the right
קדושה, kedusha, they're not going to be—he doesn't have a good one—they're
not going to be non-specified.
Anyway, let's read a little bit more in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
ליה, amar leh, he said back to him, he basically התם ולקח
ועשה אמר רחמנא. hasam velakach ve'asa amur rachmana. By the case of
birds, the תורה Torah says, you take and you do. אי בעלקיחת
בעלים אי בעשיית כהן. iba belakichas ba'alim, iba be'asiyas kohen. Its identity
is defined either at the time that the בעלים ba'alim does it,
or the כהן. kohen. These birds, which it's not yet, which didn't
have the בעלים ba'alim yet, and hasn't had the כהן kohen yet,
and the person died, so their קדושה kedusha is not specified. That's
what the תורה Torah tells you. It's not specified קדושה. kedusha. And
by the way, it's the exact same bird as a חטאת chatas
or an עולה. olah. So of course it's not going to be
able to be identified which is which. So the birds can have
a status of non-specified, that's possible. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here, מי
מצית אמרת? mi matzis amart?
Here, how could you say that it's not specified? הדין דחטאת תיקבר
עולה? hadein dechatas tikaver olah? How could you say that the one
that's a חטאת chatas should be brought as an עולה? olah? How,
you can't say not specified here, they're different animals, okay? הכא נקבה
הכא זכר. hacha nekeiva, hacha zachar. The חטאת chatas is a female,
the—the עולה's olah a male. So that's a silly question, which is
so obvious, of course it's a silly question. We can talk about
non-specified when any one could be used for it, right, when it
really could easily be any. So it was a completely bizarre question.
Oh well, by the animals, of course you see that of course
you know that it is—animals are defined as specified. Yeah, self-identified, clear,
clearly distinguished animals that fall into appropriate categories are specified. But non-distinguished
animals, right, that are all sort of generic, why shouldn't they be?
Okay, so we—so that was a bizarre question. But the basic point
is, you have the initial position which is that הלכה halakha was
basically said by money. And you have this counter-position that says we
shouldn't be limiting it to money. Whether it's money, whether it's animals,
whether it's bars of metal, if it's not specified, it's not specified.
Don't ask me from a question when you happen to have the
exact right animals, of course if you have the right animals, that's
like if you had three piles of money, one had a big
עולה olah sign and a חטאת chatas sign and a שלמים shelamim
sign you said I'm sanctifying this money. Okay, that's also not specified
because it's clear. If you have the right animals, of course it's
clear. But if you don't have the right animals, okay, the other
position says it doesn't matter whether it's money or anything else. It
all follows the same הלכה. halakha. So that's the question. Is the
הלכה halakha basically said only by money, or is it basically said
by everything? And interestingly, one of the applications is this idea of
birds. If the הלכה halakha is said not limited to money, then
this case which is the woman who buys the two birds and
gets defined when she takes it or when the כהן kohen brings
it, and she were to die, well then that would also be
seen as non-specified קדושה kedusha and the הלכה halakha would be that
we would bring both of them as an עולה. olah. Okay, so
let's read a little bit more. I think there were some questions
but I want to get a little bit further here, get a
little out of the woods here. So, מתיב רב המנונא. mative Rav
Hamnuna. רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna asked: מי
אמרינן בהמה בעלת מום כסתומה דמיא?
mi
amrinan
beheima ba'alas mum kistuma damya?
Is it really true that a בהמה בעלת מום beheima ba'alas mum
is like סתומה? stuma? Because that was the one we said that
actually would be like cash, right, if it had a מום mum
even according to the approach that limits it to cash and to
money. A בהמה beheima with a מום mum is seen as readily
liquidatable,
liquefiable, anyway, not fungible. Anyway, anyway, easily liquidated, easily turned into cash,
and that would have a status of cash. What? Like it's a
מום.
mum. Like it's a מום.
mum. Who cares it's a מום? mum? I want to plow my
field, I go to the farmers market on you know... okay, wait
a minute. If you—so according to this approach that you need cash,
but a בהמה beheima with a מום mum that doesn't have a
קדושה kedusha problem and therefore can be sold right away, is considered
like cash. תא שמע, ta shema, let me tell you this. כיצד
אמרו איש מגלח על נזירות אביו? keitzad amru ish megaleiach al nezirus
aviv? When did we say that a father—a person can
shave for his father's נזירות? nezirus?
To shave here also basically means brings the קרבנות korbanos for his
father's נזירות. nezirus.
Now this ברייתא brayta here, this is actually quoted in a chopped
up way here and it's not clear. So if you take a
quick look to ל' עמוד ב', lamed amud bais, which is where
the ברייתא brayta originally appears, I don't know originally but anyway, it's
just quoted in full there. So just turn for a minute to
ל' עמוד ב' lamed amud bais and look three lines from the
top on ל' עמוד ב'. lamed amud bais. Okay, it says the
following: כיצד אמרו איש מגלח על נזירות אביו? keitzad amru ish megaleiach
al nezirus aviv? מי שהיה אביו נזיר, mi shehaya aviv nazir, the
father was a נזיר. nazir. והפריש veheifrish והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו, v'hifrish
aviv ma'os l'neziroso, so again, father set aside money, ומת, umeis, and
the father died. Now if there wasn't a child here, then the
money we would say would go towards an עולה, olah, that's what
we've been saying. But now here's an interesting special case about what
we've been talking about.
ואמר, v'amar, the son says, הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח על מעות
אבא. hareini nazir al m'nas she'agaleach al ma'os abba. Abba, you know
what, I'll be a נזיר nazir as long as I get to
use my father's money for my קרבנות. korbanos. That's what אגלח agaleach
means. Okay, so you had this pile of money which would have
gone to an עולה olah because the נזיר nazir died, and now
the son says, you know what, I'll use that money for mine,
as long as it was, as long as number one, it was
an unspecified pile, and number two is he accepted the נזירות neziros
after his father died. So the money was no longer able to
be used for its original purpose. It was standing there with say
undefined purpose as of yet. Okay, so the father had died and
then he accepted his נזירות neziros specifically with the right, you know,
assuming he was entitled to use that money, then he actually does
get to use that money for his קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, זהו שמגלח
על מעות אביו. zehu she'm'galeach al ma'os aviv. That person gets to
bring the קרבנות korbanos with his father's money. אבל מי שהיה הוא
ואביו נזירים. aval mi shehaya hu v'aviv nezirim. He and his father
were נזירים nezirim at the same time. Okay, he didn't wait for
his father to die. והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת, v'hifrish aviv ma'os
l'neziroso umeis, and then the father died and the money had been
sanctified for the father's thing. הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה. harei elu yiplu
l'nedavah. Then you don't get to use that money for his נזירות,
neziros, that has the normal הלכה halacha that it goes towards the
עולה. olah. Okay, so that's the הלכה. halacha. Let's jump back to
our גמרא Gemara and see how it's being used. Okay, so turning
back to our גמרא, Gemara, כ"ז עמוד ב', Chaf Zayin Amud Beis,
תא שמע. ta shma.
כיצד אמרו האיש מגלח על נזירות אביו. keitzad amru ha'ish m'galeach al
neziros aviv. Okay, so it cut out the line that when it
does work, it's when the father died and then he said I'll
be a נזיר. nazir. However, היה הוא ואביו נזירים, haya hu v'aviv
nezirim, it sort of jumps to the second case. This case it
doesn't work is he and his father were
נזירים. nezirim. והפריש אביו מעות לנזירותו ומת, v'hifrish aviv ma'os l'neziroso umeis,
and the father set aside money and then the father died. ואמר
הריני נזיר על מנת שאגלח
על מעות אבא. v'amar hareini nazir al m'nas she'agaleach al ma'os abba.
And he said, I'm going to use my father's money. So he
can't do that now because he was already a נזיר nazir before
his father, you know, before his father died.
הרי אלו יפלו לנדבה. harei elu yiplu l'nedavah. Okay, in that case
he's not entitled to use the father's money and you do with
the money what you normally would do, which would be unspecified money
goes towards a נדבה. nedavah. הייתה לו בהמה מפורשת, haysa lo behemah
m'foreshas, if however the animal had been already
identified, חטאת תמות, chatas tamus, the animal that's a חטאת chatas should
die. עולה תקרב עולה, olah tikarev olah, עולה olah bring עולה. olah.
שלמים יקרבו שלמים. shlamim yikrevu shlamim. Okay, so so far doesn't say
anything, especially in that case, much new. Unspecified money goes towards an
עולה, olah, specified animals goes towards their right thing. So how are
we using this? מאי לאו, mai lav, says the גמרא, Gemara,
אפילו בעלת מום. afilu ba'alas mum. Look, when it says if you've
got the animal, you can't get to use, you don't get to
use the money for an עולה, olah, presumably by once you have
animals that sort of they're used for their right purpose, presumably that
would even include cases of non-specified animals with blemishes, which is like
crazy because that's not the case in the משנה. Mishnah. The ברייתא,
Braisa, the case is that it's very clear, this is the חטאת,
chatas, this is the עולה, olah, it is clearly explicit. But the
גמרא Gemara somehow thinks since you're contrasting money to animals, any case
of animals would be different. Any case of animals would not be
like money because it's trying to support this idea with this idea
of are animals like money or not. So presumably all cases of
animals, even non-specified animals, even animals with blemishes wouldn't be like money.
Isn't that what it's saying? So מאי לאו אפילו בעלת מום? mai
lav afilu ba'alas mum? לא, תמימה. lo, tmimah. No, we're talking about
that the animals are unblemished, or even more, that the animals are
clearly specified. אבל בעלת מום כסתומה דמי. aval ba'alas mum k'stumah dami.
One minute, so you want to tell me though that if you
had just three cows there and they had blemishes, that would have
the same status of money? That's what the argument is. So מאי
איריא מעות? mai irya ma'os? So why is it only giving the
example if you've got money you can use it to go ahead
and you know go towards an עולה? olah? So לימא הייתה לו
בהמה בעלת מום יפלו לנדבה, leima haysa lo behemah ba'alas mum yiplu
l'nedavah, meaning this is already a better question. Why you contrasting unspecified
money to specified animals, right? You're leaving off a lot of middle
cases. Go to the extreme. Right, why don't you just, yeah, so
the גמרא Gemara often goes to the extreme. Okay, be a little
bit clearer. Say if you've got unspecified animals with blemishes, then then
the money goes towards a נדבה. nedavah. But if you've got specified
animals, or even non-specified animals but they don't have blemishes, then the
money doesn't go to a נדבה, nedavah, then you're stuck, right? Why
not contrast closer cases, okay, if there really are these differences? So
it sounds like only money. Anything that's not money would be no
good. If it really are certain types of animals are like money,
animals unspecified with blemishes, why not say that? So the גמרא Gemara
says הכי נמי. hachi nami. You know what? Fine, that's included in
the idea of money. So בעלת מום למאי קדשה? ba'alas mum l'mai
kadesha? If it's got a blemish, what's the sanctity going to? לדמי.
lidmei. Ultimately it's going to be sold. So דמי היינו מעות. d'mei
haynu ma'os. So that's what we meant when we said money. Okay,
it's like sort of obvious. Money means anything that can be sold.
Which is I think how we would have read it, right? If
you said you've got a pile of unspecified money, you'd do one
thing. On the other hand, if you've sanctified your חטאת, chatat, you've
sanctified your עולה, olah, you've sanctified your שלמים, shelamim, I would have
said any case that you have not clearly identified which is your
חטאת, chatat, which is your עולה, olah, which is your שלמים, shelamim,
it goes into the money category, right? So if I had a
guess which is the bigger category, I'd assume the money category is
everything.
Exactly specifying חטאת, chatat, עולה, olah, and שלמים, shelamim, that's the case
where there's a different הלכה. halacha. And that's basically what the גמרא
Gemara is saying. Okay? So basically what we've done is, we're working
out this special הלכה halacha that unspecified money goes towards an עולה.
olah. Does it apply only to cash or things that are seen
like cash, which the גמרא Gemara is willing to consider maybe animals
with a מום mum or whatever? Or does it basically apply to
like pretty much everything, okay? And even within the idea that it's
only things like cash, there's a question of like exactly where do
you put the בהמה behema with a מום? mum? Is the בהמה
behema with a מום mum in the cash category or in the
non-cash category? But again, this is an assumption that this is a
formal הלכה halacha of a pile of money, or this is one
approach in the גמרא Gemara that we started with. Right, there's pushback
and it says it should be not so limited, but the limiting
approach is it only basically applies to money and to other things
that we're willing to consider to be like cash, among them is
animals with a מום mum that the קדושה kedushah doesn't become an
obstacle and they're seen as something that's able to be sold pretty
regularly. All right, so I didn't get to your questions, but we're
going to end here because at least we've